[This talk contains graphic language Viewer discretion is advised] So, this is the first and the last slide each of my 6,400 students over the last 15 years has seen. I do not believe you can build a multibillion-dollar organization unless you are clear on which instinct or organ you are targeting. Our species has a need for a superbeing. Our competitive advantage as a species is our brain. Our brain is robust enough to ask these really difficult questions, but, unfortunately, it doesn't have the processing power to answer them, which creates a need for a superbeing that we can pray to and look to for answers. What is prayer? Sending a query into the universe, and hopefully there's some sort of divine intervention -- we don't need to understand what's going on -- from an all-knowing, all-seeing superbeing that gives us authority that this is the right answer. "Will my kid be all right?" You have your planet of stuff, you have your planet of work, you have your planet of friends. If you have kids, you know that once something comes off the rails with your kids, everything melts, in your universe to the Sun that is your kids. "Will my kid be all right?" "Symptoms and treatment of croup" in the Google query box. One in six queries presented to Google have never been asked before in the history of mankind. What priest, teacher, rabbi, scholar, mentor, boss has so much credibility that one in six questions posed to that person have never been asked before? Google is our modern man's God. Imagine your face and your name above everything you've put into that box, and you're going to realize you trust Google more than any entity in your history. (Laughter) Let's move further down the torso. One of the other wonderful things about our species is we not only need to be loved, but we need to love others. Children with poor nutrition but a lot of affection have better outcomes than children with good nutrition and poor affection. However, the best signal that you might make it to be part of the number-one fastest growing demographic in the world -- centenarians, people who live to triple digits -- there are three signals. In reverse order: your genetics -- not as important as you'd like to think, so you can continue to treat your body like shit and think, "Oh, Uncle Joe lived to 95, the die have been cast." It's less important than you think. Number two is lifestyle. Don't smoke, don't be obese, and prescreen -- get rid of about two-thirds of early cancers and cardiovascular disease. The number one indicator or signal that you'll make it to triple digits: How many people do you love? Caretaking is the security camera -- we call the low-resolution security camera in our brain -- deciding whether or not you are adding value. Facebook taps into our instinctive need not only to be loved, but to love others, mostly through pictures that create empathy, catalyze and reinforce our relationships. Let's continue our journey down the torso. Amazon is our consumptive gut. The instinct of more is hardwired into us. The penalty for too little is starvation and malnutrition. Open your cupboards, open your closets, you have 10 to 100x times what you need. Why? Because the penalty for too little is much greater than the penalty for too much. So "more for less" is a business strategy that never goes out of style. It's the strategy of China, it's a the strategy of Walmart, and now it's the strategy of the most successful company in the world, Amazon. You get more for less into your gut; digest, send it to your muscular and skeletal system of consumption. Moving further, once we know we will survive, the basic instinct, we move to the second most powerful instinct, and that is to spread and select the strongest, smartest and fastest seed to the four corners of the earth, or pick the best seed. This is not a timepiece. I haven't wound it in five years. It's my vain attempt to say to people, "If you mate with me, your children are more likely to survive than if you mate with someone wearing a Swatch watch." (Laughter) The key to business is tapping into the irrational organs. "Irrational" is Harvard Business School's and New York Business School's term for fat profit margins and shareholder value. "High-caloric paste for your children." No? You love your choosy mom. Why choosy moms choose Jif: you love your kids more. The greatest algorithm for shareholder creation from World War II to the advent of Google was taking an average product and appealing to people's hearts. You're a better a mom, a better person, a better patriot if you buy this average soap versus this average soap. Now, the number one algorithm for shareholder value isn't technology. Look at the Forbes 400. Take out inherited wealth, take out finance. The number one source of wealth creation: appealing to your reproductive organs. The Lauders; the number one wealthiest man in Europe, LVMH. Numbers two and three: H&M and Inditex. You want to target the most irrational organs for shareholder value. As a result, these four companies -- Apple, Amazon, Facebook and Google -- have disarticulated who we are. God, love, consumption, sex. The proportion in your approach to those things is who you are, and they have reassembled who we are in the form of for-profit companies. At the end of the Great Recession, the market capitalization of these companies was equivalent to the GDP of Niger. Now it is equivalent to the GDP of India, having blown past Russia and Canada in '13 and '14. There are only five nations that have a GDP greater than the combined market capitalization of these four firms. Something is happening, though. The conversation just a year ago was, which CEO was more Jesus-like? Who was running for president? Now the worm has turned. Everything they're doing is bothering us. We're worried they're tax avoiders. Walmart, since the Great Recession, has paid 64 billion dollars in corporate income tax; Amazon has paid 1.4. How do we pay our firefighters, our soldiers and our social workers if the most successful companies in the world don't pay their fair share? Pretty easy. That means the less successful companies have to pay more than their fair share. Alexa, is this a good thing? This is despite that fact -- (Laughter) This is despite the fact that Amazon has added the entire market capitalization of Walmart to its market cap in the last 19 months. Whose fault is it? It's our fault. We're electing regulators who don't have the backbone to actually go after these companies. Facebook lies to EU regulators and says, "It would be impossible for us to share the data between our core platform and our proposed acquisition of WhatsApp. Approve the merger." They approve the merger and then -- spoiler alert! -- they figure it out. And the EU says, "I feel lied to. We're fining you 120 [million] dollars," about .6 percent of the acquisition price of 19 billion dollars. If Mark Zuckerberg could take out an insurance policy that the acquisition would go through for .6 percent, wouldn't he do it? Anticompetitive behavior. A two-and-a-half-billion-dollar fine, three billion of the cash flow, three percent of the cash on Google's balance sheet. We are telling these companies, "The smart thing to do, the shareholder-driven thing to do, is to lie and to cheat." We are issuing 25-cent parking tickets on a meter that costs 100 dollars an hour. The smart thing to do is lie. Job destruction! Amazon only needs one person for two at Macy's. If they grow their business 20 billion dollars this year, which they will, we will lose 53,000 cashiers and clerks. This is nothing unusual; this has happened all through our economy, we've just never seen companies this good at it. That's one Yankee Stadium of workers. It's even worse in media. If Facebook and Google grow their businesses 22 billion dollars this year, which they will, we're going to lose approximately 150,000 creative directors, planners and copywriters. Or we can fill up two-and-a-half Yankee Stadiums and say, "You are out of work, courtesy of Amazon." We now get the majority of our news from our social media feeds, and the majority of our news coming off of social media feeds is ... fake news. (Laughter) I am not allowed to be political or use curse words, or talk about religion in class, so I can definitely not say, "Zuckerberg has become Putin's bitch." I definitely cannot say that. (Laughter) Their defense: "Facebook is not a media company; it's a technology company." You create original content, you pay sports leagues to give you original content, you run advertising against it -- boom! -- you're a media company. Just in the last few days, Sheryl Sandberg has repeated this lie, that "We are not a media company." Facebook has openly embraced the margins of celebrity and the influence of a media company yet seems to be allergic to the responsibilities of a media company. Imagine McDonald's. We find 80 percent of their beef is fake, and it's giving us encephalitis, and we're making terrible decisions. And we say, "McDonald's, we're pissed off!" And they say, "Wait, wait -- we're not a fast-food restaurant, we're a fast-food platform." (Laughter) These companies and CEOs wrap themselves in a neon-blue pink rainbow and blue blanket to create an illusionist trick from their behavior each day, which is more indicative of the spawn of Darth Vader and Ayn Rand. Why? Because we as progressives are seen as nice but weak. If Sheryl Sandberg had written a book on gun rights or on the pro-life movement, would they be flying Sheryl to Cannes? No. And I'm not doubting their progressive values, but it foots to shareholder value, because we as progressives are seen as weak. They're so nice -- remember Microsoft? They didn't seem as nice, and regulators stepped in much earlier than the regulators now, who would never step in on those nice, nice people. I'm about to get on a plane tonight, and I'm going to have a guy named Roy from TSA molest me. If I am suspected of a DUI on the way home, I can have blood taken from my person. But wait! Don't tap into the iPhone -- it's sacred. This is our new cross. It shouldn't be the iPhone X, it should be called the "iPhone Cross." We have our religion; it's Apple. Our Jesus Christ is Steve Jobs, and we've decided this is holier than our person, our house or our computer. We have become totally out of control with the gross idolatry of innovation and of youth. We no longer worship at the altar of character, of kindness, but of innovation and people who create shareholder value. Amazon has become so powerful in the marketplace, it can conduct Jedi mind tricks. It can begin damaging other industries just by looking at them. Nike announces they're distributing on Amazon, their stock goes up, every other footwear stock goes down. When Amazon stock goes up, the rest of retail stocks go down, because they assume what's good for Amazon is bad for everybody else. They cut the cost on salmon 33 percent when they acquired Whole Foods. In between the time they announced the acquisition of Whole Foods and when it closed, Kroger, the largest pure-play grocer in America, shed a third of its value, because Amazon purchased a grocer one-eleventh the size of Kroger. I got very lucky. I predicted the acquisition of Whole Foods by Amazon the week before it happened. This is me boasting; I said this publicly in the media. This was the largest acquisition in their history, they'd never made an acquisition over a billion, and people asked, "How did you know this?" So I'm letting this very impressive audience in on the secret. How did I know this? I'm going to tell you how I knew. I bark at Alexa all day long and try to figure out what's going on. (Scott Galloway) Alexa, buy whole milk. (Alexa) I couldn't find anything for whole milk, so I've added whole milk to your shopping list. SG: Then I asked, (SG) Alexa, buy organic foods. (Alexa) The top search result for organic food is Plum Organics baby food, banana and pumpkin, 12-pack of four ounces each. It's 15 dollars total. Would you like to buy it? SG: And then, as often happens at my age, I got confused. (SG) Alexa, buy whole foods. (Alexa) I have purchased the outstanding stock of Whole Foods Incorporated at 42 dollars per share. I have charged 13.7 billion to your American Express card. (Laughter) SG: I thought that'd be funnier. We've personified these companies, and just as when you're really angry over every little thing someone does in your life and relationships, you've got to ask yourself, "What's going on here? Why are we so disappointed in technology?" I believe it's because the ratio of one-percent pursuit of shareholder value and 99 percent the betterment of humanity that technology used to play has been flipped, and now we're totally focused on shareholder value instead of humanity. One hundred thousand people came together for the Manhattan Project and literally saved the world. Technology saved the world. My mother was a four-year-old Jew living in London at the outset of the war. If we had not won the footrace towards splitting the atom, would she have survived? It's unlikely. Twenty-five years later, the most impressive accomplishment, arguably, ever in all of humankind: put a man on the moon. Four hundred thirty thousand Canadians, British and Americans came together, again, with very basic technology, and put a man on the moon. Now we have the 700,000 best and brightest, and these are the best and brightest from the four corners of the earth. They are literally playing with lasers relative to slingshots, relative to the squirt gun. They have the GDP of India to work at. And after studying these companies for 10 years, I know what their mission is. Is it to organize the world's information? Is it to connect us? Is it to create greater comity of man? It isn't. I know why we have brought together -- I know that the greatest collection of IQ capital and creativity, that their sole mission is: to sell another fucking Nissan. My name is Scott Galloway, I teach at NYU, and I appreciate your time. (Applause) Chris Anderson: Not planned, but you prompted some questions in me, Scott. (Laughter) That was a spectacular rant. SG: Is this like Letterman? When you do well, he calls you onto the couch? CA: No, no, you're going to the heart of the conversation right now. Everyone's aware that after years of worshipping Silicon Valley, suddenly the worm has turned and in such a big way. To some people here, it will just feel like you're piling on, you're kicking the kids who've already been kicked to pieces anyway. Don't you feel any empathy for them at all? SG: None whatsoever. Look, this is the issue: it's not their fault, it's our fault. They're for-profit companies. They're not concerned with the condition of our souls. They're not going to take care of us when we get older. We have set up a society that values shareholder value over everything, and they're doing what they're supposed to be doing. But we need to elect people, and we need to force ourselves to force them to be subject to the same scrutiny that the rest of business endures, full stop. CA: There's another narrative that is arguably equally consistent with the facts, which is that there actually is good intent in much of the leadership -- I won't say everyone, necessarily -- many of the employees. We all know people who work in those companies, and they still are pretty convincing that their mission is to -- so, the alternative narrative is that there have been unintended consequences here, that the technologies that we're unleashing, the algorithms, that we're attempting to personalize the internet, for example, have A, resulted in weird effects like filter bubbles that we weren't expecting; and B, made themselves vulnerable to weird things like -- oh, I don't know, Russian hackers creating accounts and doing things that we didn't expect. Isn't the unintended consequence a possibility here? SG: I don't think -- I'm pretty sure, statistically, they're no less or better people than any other organization that has 100,000 or more people. I don't think they're bad people. As a matter of fact, I would argue that there's a lot of very civic-minded, decent leadership. But this is the issue: when you control 90 percent points of share in a market, search, that is now bigger than the entire advertising market of any nation, and you're primarily compensated and trying to develop economic security for you and the families of your employees, to increase that market share, you can't help but leverage all the power at your disposal. And that is the basis for regulation, and it's the basis for the truism throughout history that power corrupts. They're not bad people; we've just let them get out of control. CA: So maybe the case is slightly overstated? I know at least a bit -- Larry Page, for example, Jeff Bezos -- I don't actually believe they wake up thinking, "I've got to sell a fucking Nissan." I don't think they think that. I think they are trying to build something cool, and are probably, in moments of reflection, as horrified that some of the things that have happened as we might be. So is there a different way of framing this, to say that when your model is advertising, that there are dangers there that you have to take on more explicitly? SG: I think it's very difficult to set an organization up as we do, to pursue shareholder value above all else. They're not non-profits. The reason people go to work there is they want to create economic security for them and their families, mostly first and foremost. And when you get to a point where you control so much economic power, you use all the weapons at your disposal. I don't think they're bad people, but I think the role of government and the role of us as consumers and people who elect our officials is to ensure that there are some checks here. And we have given them the mother of all hall passes because we find them just so fascinating. CA: Scott, eloquently put, spectacularly put. Mark Zuckerberg, Jeff Bezos, Larry Page, Tim Cook, if you're watching, you're welcome to come and make the counterargument as well. Scott, thank you so much. SG: Thanks very much. (Applause)
[Esta charla contiene lenguaje obsceno. Se recomienda discreción del espectador] Esta es la primera y la última diapositiva que cada uno de mis 6400 estudiantes ha visto en los últimos 15 años. No creo que se pueda construir una organización multimillonaria a menos que se tenga claro a qué instinto u órgano se dirige. Nuestra especie tiene una necesidad de superación. Nuestra ventaja competitiva como especie es nuestro cerebro. Nuestro cerebro es lo bastante robusto para hacer preguntas difíciles, pero, desafortunadamente, carece del poder de procesamiento para responderlas, lo que crea la necesidad de un superhumano al que poder rezar y acudir en busca de respuestas. ¿Qué es una plegaria? Enviar una consulta al universo, y que con suerte haya algún tipo de intervención divina, sin saber lo que está pasando, de un ser omnisciente que todo lo sabe y que todo lo ve que garantiza darnos la respuesta correcta. "¿Va a estar bien mi hijo?" Tenemos el planeta de las cosas, el planeta del trabajo, el planeta de los amigos. Si tienen hijos, saben que si algo sale mal con sus hijos, todo se desmorona, en el universo hasta el sol son los hijos. "¿Va a estar bien mi hijo?" "Síntomas y tratamiento de crup" en la casilla de búsqueda de Google. Una de cada seis consultas enviadas a Google nunca se ha preguntado antes en la historia de la humanidad. ¿Qué sacerdote, maestro, rabino, erudito, mentor o jefe tiene tanta credibilidad que una de cada seis preguntas planteadas a esa persona nunca se ha preguntado antes? Google es el dios de nuestro ser humano moderno. Imaginen su rostro y su nombre por encima de todo lo que han puesto en esa casilla, y se darán cuenta de que confían más en Google que en cualquier entidad en su historia. (Risas) Avancemos más abajo en el torso. Otra de las cosas maravillosas sobre nuestra especie es que no solo necesitamos ser amados, sino que necesitamos amar a los demás. Los niños con nutrición deficiente pero que reciben mucho afecto tienen mejor rendimiento que los niños con buena nutrición y afecto deficiente. Sin embargo, la mejor señal de que Uds. pueden ser parte del grupo demográfico número uno con mayor crecimiento en el mundo, —centenarios, personas que viven hasta llegar a los tres dígitos— se determina por tres hechos. En orden inverso: la genética, que no es tan importante como nos gustaría creer, así que pueden seguir tratando su cuerpo como una porquería y pensar: "El tío Juan vivió hasta los 95, la suerte está echada". Esto es menos importante de lo que piensan. Número dos, el estilo de vida. No fumen, no sean obesos y pasen controles para no ser uno de los dos tercios con cánceres tempranos y enfermedades cardiovasculares. El indicador o señal número uno que los hará llegar a tres dígitos: ¿A cuántas personas aman? Cuidar es la cámara de seguridad, —llamamos a la cámara de seguridad de baja resolución de nuestro cerebro— que decide si se añade valor o no. Facebook aprovecha nuestra necesidad instintiva no solo de ser amado, sino de amar a los demás, principalmente a través de imágenes que crean empatía, catalizan y refuerzan nuestras relaciones. Continuemos nuestro viaje por el torso. Amazon es nuestro instinto de consumo. El instinto de aún más está integrado en nosotros. El castigo por tener muy poco es la inanición y la desnutrición. Abran sus armarios, tienen entre 10 y 100 veces más de lo que necesitan. ¿Por qué? Porque el castigo por tener muy poco es mucho mayor que la penalización por tener demasiado. "Más por menos" es una estrategia de negocios que nunca pasa de moda. Es la estrategia de China, es una estrategia de Walmart, y ahora es la estrategia de la compañía más exitosa del mundo, Amazon. Obtienen más por menos para su instinto; lo digerimos y enviamos a nuestro sistema de consumo muscular y esquelético. Avancemos. una vez que sabemos que sobreviviremos, el instinto básico, nos vamos al segundo instinto más poderoso. Es propagar y seleccionar la semilla más fuerte, más inteligente y más rápida por toda la tierra, o elegir la mejor semilla. Esto no es un reloj. No le he dado cuerda en cinco años. Es mi vano intento de decirle a la gente, "Si te apareas conmigo, es más probable que tus hijos sobrevivan que si te apareas con alguien que usa un reloj Swatch". (Risas) La clave del negocio es aprovechar los órganos irracionales. "Irracional", el término de Harvard Business School y New York Business School para grandes márgenes de ganancia y valor para el accionista. "Pasta de alto contenido calórico para sus hijos". ¿No? Uno ama a su mamá exigente. ¿Por qué las mamás exigentes eligen a Jif? Porque aman más a sus hijos. El mayor algoritmo para la creación de accionistas de la 2ª Guerra Mundial en el desarrollo de Google fue tomar un producto promedio y apelar al corazón de las personas. Eres una mejor mamá, mejor persona, mejor patriota si compras este jabón promedio en vez de este jabón promedio. El algoritmo número uno para el valor del accionista no es la tecnología. Miren el Forbes 400. Al margen de la riqueza heredada, y de las finanzas. La fuente número uno de creación de riqueza: es apelar a sus órganos reproductivos. Los Lauder; el hombre más rico de Europa, LVMH. Números dos y tres: H&M e Inditex. Se desea apuntar a los órganos más irracionales para el valor del accionista. Como resultado, estas cuatro compañías: Apple, Amazon, Facebook y Google, han desarticulado quienes somos. Dios, amor, consumo, sexo. La proporción en el enfoque de esas cosas es quién es uno, y han remodelado quiénes somos en forma de compañías con fines de lucro. Al final de la Gran Recesión, la capitalización bursátil de estas compañías era equivalente al PIB de Níger. Ahora es equivalente al PIB de India, habiendo superado al de Rusia y Canadá en 13 y 14. Solo hay cinco naciones que tienen un PBI mayor que la capitalización de mercado combinada de estas cuatro empresas. Sin embargo, algo está sucediendo. La conversación hace solo un año fue, ¿qué CEO era más parecido a Jesús? ¿Quién se postulaba para presidente? Ahora la paciencia se ha acabado. Todo lo que están haciendo es molestarnos. Nos preocupa que sean evasores de impuestos. Walmart, desde la Gran Recesión, ha pagado USD 64 000 millones en impuestos de sociedades. Amazon ha pagado 1400. ¿Cómo pagamos a nuestros soldados, bomberos y trabajadores sociales, si las empresas más exitosas del mundo no pagan su parte proporcional? Muy fácil. Eso significa que las empresas menos exitosas tienen que pagar más que su parte justa. Alexa, ¿esto es algo bueno? Esto a pesar de ese hecho (Risas) Esto es a pesar del hecho de que Amazon ha agregado la capitalización del completo mercado de Walmart a su capitalización del mercado en los últimos 19 meses. ¿De quién es la culpa? Es nuestra culpa. Elegimos reguladores que no tienen el coraje de perseguir realmente a estas compañías. Facebook miente a los reguladores de la UE y dice: "Sería imposible compartir los datos entre nuestra plataforma central y nuestra propuesta de adquirir WhatsApp. Aprueben la fusión". Aprueban la fusión y luego, ¡se dan cuenta! Y la UE dice: "Me siento engañada. Les multamos con USD 120 000 millones". un 0,6 % del precio de adquisición de USD 19 000 millones. Si Mark Zuckerberg pudiera contratar una póliza de seguro de adquisición por un 0,6 %, ¿no lo haría? Comportamiento anticompetitivo. Una multa de USD 2500 millones, USD 3000 millones del flujo de efectivo, es el 3 % del efectivo en el balance de resultados de Google. Le decimos a estas compañías: "Lo más inteligente que hay que hacer, teniendo en mente a los accionistas, es mentir y hacer trampa". Emitiendo boletos de estacionamiento de 25 centavos en un medidor que cuesta USD 100 por hora. Lo más inteligente es mentir. ¡Destrucción del trabajo! Amazon solo necesita una persona por dos en Macy's. Si hacen crecer su negocio USD 20 000 millones este año, que lo harán, perderemos 53 000 cajeros y empleados. Esto no es nada inusual; ha sucedido en toda nuestra economía, nunca hemos visto empresas tan buenas en eso. Ese es un estadio de los Yankee lleno de trabajadores. Es aún peor en los medios. Si Facebook y Google hacen crecer sus negocios USD 22 000 millones este año, que lo harán, perderemos unos 150 000 directores creativos, planificadores y redactores. O podemos llenar dos estadios y medio de los Yankee y decir: "Estás sin trabajo, por cortesía de Amazon". Obtenemos la mayoría de nuestras noticias por nuestros medios sociales, y la mayoría de nuestras noticias que provienen de los medios sociales son... noticias falsas. (Risas) No se me permite ser político, usar malas palabras, o hablar de religión aquí, así que definitivamente no puedo decir: "Zuckerberg se ha convertido en la puta de Putin". Definitivamente no puedo decir eso. (Risas) Su defensa: "Facebook no es una compañía de medios, es una compañía de tecnología". Uds. crean el contenido original, pagan ligas deportivas para que les den contenido original, Uds. reciben publicidad para eso, ¡bum!, son una compañía de medios. Solo en los últimos días, Sheryl Sandberg repite esa mentira de que "no somos una compañía de medios". Facebook ha abrazado abiertamente los márgenes de celebridad y la influencia de una compañía de medios sin embargo, parece ser alérgica a la responsabilidad de una compañía de medios. Piensen en McDonald's. Encontramos que el 80 % de su carne es falsa, y nos está dando encefalitis, y estamos tomando decisiones terribles y decimos: "McDonald's, ¡estamos enojados!" Y dicen: "Esperen, esperen... no somos un restaurante de comida rápida, somos una plataforma de comida rápida". (Risas) Estas compañías y sus CEOs se envuelven en un arcoíris rosado de neón y una manta azul para crear un truco ilusionista de su comportamiento todos los días, que es más indicativo del engendro de Darth Vader y Ayn Rand. ¿Por qué? Porque nosotros, como progresistas, somos buenos pero débiles. Si Sheryl Sandberg hubiera escrito un libro sobre derechos de armas o sobre el movimiento pro-vida, ¿estarían volando Sheryl a Cannes? No. Y no dudo de sus valores progresistas, pero se basa en el valor para el accionista, porque nosotros como progresistas somos vistos como débiles. Son muy buenos, ¿recuerdan Microsoft? No parecían tan agradables, y los reguladores intervinieron mucho antes que los reguladores actuales, que nunca intervendrían a esas personas lindas y agradables. Estoy a punto de tomar un avión esta noche, y tendré a un tipo llamado Roy de la TSA que me molesta. Si sospechan que tengo influencia de alcohol camino a casa, me pueden sacar sangre. ¡Pero esperen! No toquen el iPhone, es sagrado. Esta es nuestra nueva cruz. No debería ser el iPhone X, debería llamarse "iPhone Cruz". Tenemos nuestra religión, se llama Apple. Nuestro Jesucristo es Steve Jobs, y hemos decidido que esto es más santo que nuestra persona, nuestra casa o nuestra computadora. Estamos totalmente descontrolados con la gran idolatría de la innovación y de la juventud. Ya no adoramos en el altar la bondad, sino de innovación y personas que crean valor para los accionistas. Amazon se ha vuelto tan poderosa en el mercado, que puede llevar a cabo trucos mentales Jedi. Puede comenzar a dañar otras industrias con solo mirarlas. Nike anuncia que distribuyen en Amazon, sus acciones aumentan, todas las demás acciones de calzado caen. Al subir las acciones de Amazon, el resto de las acciones minoristas bajan, porque suponen que lo que es bueno para Amazon es malo para el resto. Redujeron el costo del salmón al 33 % al adquirir Whole Foods. Entre el momento en que anunciaron la adquisición de Whole Foods y cuando se cerró, Kroger, el mayor supermercado online de EE.UU. arrojó un tercio de sus resultados, porque Amazon compró un supermercado de un undécimo del tamaño de Kroger. Tuve mucha suerte. Predije la adquisición de Whole Foods por Amazon la semana antes de que sucediera. Este soy yo jactándome. Lo dije públicamente en los medios. Esta fue la adquisición más grande en su historia, nunca habían hecho una adquisición de más de mil millones, y la gente preguntó: "¿Cómo lo supiste?" Así que expondré ante esta audiencia tan impresionante el secreto. ¿Cómo lo sé? Les diré cómo lo supe. Llamo la atención de Alexa todo el día y trato de descubrir qué está pasando. (Scott Galloway) Alexa, compra leche entera. (Alexa) No pude encontrar nada para la leche entera, así que agregué leche entera a tu lista de compras. SG: Entonces pregunté, (SG) Alexa, compra alimentos orgánicos. (Alexa) El resultado de búsqueda es superior para comida orgánica. Plum Organics es comida para bebés, bananas y calabaza, 12 paquetes de 100 gr cada uno. Son USD 15 en total. ¿Te gustaría comprarlo? SG: Y luego, como sucede a menudo a mi edad, me confundí. (SG) Alexa, compra alimentos integrales. (Alexa) Compré acciones excedentes de Whole Foods Incorporated a USD 42 por acción. He cargado 13 700 millones en su tarjeta American Express. (Risas) SG: Pensé que sería más divertido. Hemos personificado estas compañías, al igual que cuando uno está enojado por cada pequeña cosa que hace en su vida y sus relaciones, hay que preguntarse: "¿Qué pasa aquí? ¿Por qué estamos tan decepcionados con la tecnología?" Creo que es porque la proporción del 1 % de búsqueda del valor para el accionista y el 99 % de la mejora de la humanidad que solía dar esa tecnología se ha invertido y ahora nos enfocamos solo en el valor para los accionistas en lugar de la humanidad. Cien mil personas se reunieron para el Proyecto Manhattan y literalmente salvó al mundo. La tecnología salvó al mundo. Mi madre era una judía de cuatro años que vivía en Londres al inicio de la guerra. Si no hubiésemos ganado la carrera hacia la división del átomo, ¿ella habría sobrevivido? No es probable. Veinticinco años después, el logro más impresionante, posiblemente, en toda la humanidad: poner a un hombre en la luna 430 000 canadienses, británicos y estadounidenses se reunieron, de nuevo, con tecnología muy básica, y llevaron a un hombre a la luna. Ahora tenemos los 700 000 mejores y más brillantes, y estos son los mejores y más brillantes de los cuatro cantos de la tierra. Están jugando literalmente con láser en relación con las hondas, en relación con la pistola de agua. Tienen el PIB de India para trabajar en ello. Y después de estudiar estas compañías durante 10 años, sé cuál es su misión. ¿Es organizar la información del mundo? ¿Es conectarnos? ¿Es crear un mayor compromiso humano? No lo es. Sé por qué los hemos reunido. Sé que la mayor colección de capital de CI y creatividad, tiene como única misión vender otro jodido Nissan. Mi nombre es Scott Galloway, enseño en NYU y aprecio su tiempo. (Aplausos) Chris Anderson: Sin planearlo, me suscitaste algunas preguntas, Scott. (Risas) Esa fue una diatriba espectacular. SG: ¿Es esto como Letterman? Cuando lo haces bien, ¿él te llama al sofá? CA: No, no, vas al corazón de la conversación en este momento. Todos saben que después de años de adorar a Silicon Valley, de repente, se acabó la paciencia de manera monumental. Algunas personas aquí sentirán como si estuvieras aumentando la presión, estás pateando a los niños que ya han sido pateados de todos modos. ¿No sientes empatía por ellos? SG: Ninguna en absoluto. Mira, este es el problema: no es su culpa, es nuestra culpa. Son compañías con fines de lucro. No les preocupa la condición de nuestras almas. No nos van a cuidar cuando seamos mayores. Hemos creado una sociedad que valora el valor para los accionistas sobre todo, y están haciendo lo que se supone que deben hacer. Pero tenemos que elegir personas, y tenemos que obligarnos a forzarlos, a que estén sujetos al mismo escrutinio que el resto de los negocios, punto. CA: Hay otra narrativa posible y que es igualmente consistente con los hechos, de que realmente hay buenas intenciones en gran parte del liderazgo. No digo todos, necesariamente, muchos de los empleados. Todos conocemos a personas que trabajan en esas empresas, y todavía son bastante convincentes de cuál es su misión: Y la narrativa alternativa es que ha habido consecuencias no deseadas, que las tecnologías que estamos desencadenando, los algoritmos que intentamos personalizar en Internet, por ejemplo, resultaron en efectos extraños, como los filtros burbuja que no esperábamos; y se hicieron vulnerables a cosas raras como hackers rusos que crean cuentas y hacen cosas que no esperábamos. ¿No es posible aquí la consecuencia involuntaria? SG: No creo. Estoy bastante seguro, estadísticamente, no son menos ni mejores personas que cualquier otra organización con 100 000 o más personas. No creo que sean malas personas. De hecho, diría que hay mucho liderazgo decente y de mentalidad cívica. Pero este es el problema: cuando controlas el 90 % de los puntos de las acciones de un mercado, que es más grande que todo el mercado publicitario de cualquier nación, y se te recompensa e intentas desarrollar seguridad económica para ti y las familias de tus empleados, para aumentar esa cuota de mercado, no puedes evitar aprovechar toda la potencia a tu disposición. Y esa es la base de la regulación, y es la base de la perogrullada a lo largo de la historia: el poder corrompe. No son malas personas; hemos dejado que estén fuera de control. CA: ¿Entonces tal vez el caso es un poco exagerado? Sé al menos un poco... Larry Page, por ejemplo, Jeff Bezos... realmente no creo que se despierten pensando: "Tengo que vender un maldito Nissan". No creo que ellos piensen eso. Creo que tratan de construir algo genial y, probablemente, en momentos de reflexión, están horrorizados por algunas cosas que han sucedido. Y, ¿hay una forma diferente de encarar esto? ¿De decir que cuando tu modelo se anuncia, hay peligros que tienes que asumir más explícitamente? SG: Creo que es muy difícil establecer una organización como lo hacemos, buscar el valor para los accionistas por encima de todo. No son organizaciones sin fines de lucro. La razón por la que las personas trabajan allí es porque quieren crear seguridad económica para ellos y sus familias, principalmente por eso. Y cuando llegas a controlar tanto poder económico, usas todas las armas a tu disposición. No creo que sean malas personas, pero creo que el papel del gobierno y nuestro papel como consumidores y como personas que elegimos a nuestros funcionarios es asegurarnos de que haya algunos controles aquí. Y les hemos dado todos los pases porque los encontramos simplemente fascinantes. CA: Scott, muy elocuente y espectacularmente planteado. Mark Zuckerberg, Jeff Bezos, Larry Page, Tim Cook, si están mirando, pueden venir y hacer el contraargumento también. Scott, muchas gracias. SG: Muchas gracias. (Aplausos)